Today's דף daf is ס, samech, but we pick up with the
משנה mishnah on נט עמוד ב nun tet amud bet and we
are looking at the different ways in which מנחות menachos are made
or the different types of מנחות menachos I should say. And the
משנה mishnah on נט עמוד א nun tet amud aleph listed that
there are some מנחות menachos that get oil and לבונה, levonah, frankincense,
some get one or the other, and some get neither. Those that
get neither specifically is the מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei for the sin
when it's a variation of a קרבן עולה ויורד, Korban Oleh V'Yored,
a certain type of a קרבן korban that what you bring varies
based on the person's economic ability, and for the סוטה. sotah. Now
in both of those cases the תורה Torah says לא ישים עליה
שמן ולא יתן
עליה לבונה. lo yasim aleha shemen v'lo yiten aleha levonah. You cannot
put on it oil or לבונה levonah and that actually is a
negative prohibition. So this משנה mishnah deals with the negative prohibition of
putting oil and לבונה levonah on specifically the מנחה minchah of a
חוטא chotei and the מנחה minchah for a סוטה, sotah, the מנחת
קנאות. Minchas Kenaos. So let's take a look. So here we go.
וחייב על השמן בפני עצמו וחייב על לבונה בפני עצמה. v'chayav al
hashemen bifnei atzmo v'chayav al levonah bifnei atzmah. So in the משנה,
mishnah, you transgress for the oil alone and for the לבונה levonah
alone even if you only do one you transgress. ונתן
עליה שמן פסלה. v'nasan aleha shemen pasalah. If you put on it
oil you've invalidated it, so not only have you transgressed but you've
invalidated, you can't use the מנחה minchah anymore. לבונה levonah if you
put on it לבונה levonah then there's a way to fix it,
ילקטנה, yelaktenah, then just pick off the לבונה levonah because לבונה levonah
is more like a solid. Yeah but not only is it a
solid but it's not like salt, it's more
like rock candy, like crystals, like we've discussed before so somebody looked
it up on the web. So anyway so that's easier to just
pick
up, not just that it's a solid, it's also like it really
is like these rock-like things, or pebble-like things. Okay, so pick it
up and then it's still כשרה, kasher, which is interesting so you
transgress even though you can fix it. נתן שמן על שיריה אינו
עובר בלא תעשה. nasan shemen al sheyareha eino over b'lo saaseh. Although
we have learned that if you make the remnant of a מנחה
minchah חמץ chametz you transgress, לא תעשה חמץ מחלקם, lo seiaseh chametz
mechlekam, if you put oil on the remnant of a מנחה minchah
you do not transgress. It is only putting it on before what?
Does not even clear that it's a problem. It's just contrasting it
to the חמץ. chametz. So if you let a מנחה minchah become
חמץ chametz after it's offered up you transgress, if you put oil
afterwards you do not. נתן כלי על גבי כלי לא פסלה. nasan
kli al gabi kli lo pasalah. And even though we said the
oil
invalidated, what does it mean to be נתן וישים עליה שמן? nasan
v'yasim aleha shemen? Let's say you had a vessel of oil, a
little bowl of oil, and you turned it on top of your
מנחה. minchah. So then you would not invalidate, you'd just remove it,
presumably you also wouldn't transgress. That's not what we mean when we
say לא ישים עליה שמן. lo yasim aleha shemen. We don't mean
put it in a vessel on top of it and that would
not be a problem. So let's take a look.
Yes, didn't we say that things like let's say
that you can fix, I'm blanking on the case overall, that you're
not over on, is it לאו הניתק לעשה lav hanitak laaseh or
something like that, then or I don't know if that's the right
one. In other words, if you can take the לבונה levonah off
why would you be transgressing?
Is it one of these things
where well there's no עשה, aseh, it is too reversible but there
are things that are reversible you still transgress. You can turn the
lights on on שבת Shabbos and turn them back off and you
still transgress.
Well no, because turning it off is
also.
Even if it weren't you would still have transgressed.
Well I thought that's not.
I understand but you need there to be a specific מצות עשה
mitzvas aseh to be call it a ניתק לעשה. nitak laaseh. It
doesn't matter that it's physically reversible. Okay, so let's take a look.
He to the כהן kohen or to the person, the donor of
the מנחה? minchah?
Whoever does it. I mean it's true, it could be done by
the owner or by the person.
But they're not able to go to the מזבח, mizbeach, right?
No, but you could put the שמן shemen or the לבונה levonah
on beforehand. Now it would have to already as we saw before
by חמץ chametz already have been נתקדש בכלי, niskiadesh b'kli, because if
it's not נתקדש בכלי niskiadesh b'kli what makes this a מנחה minchah
to say that I've
transgressed, so but some of the מנחות, menachos, I mean we have
not yet sort of done the step-by-step process about when it's put
in a כלי kli but some of it like we see that
קידוש כלי kidush kli happens when you add the oil and that
can happen actually before it's given to the כהן. kohen. The כהן
kohen only starts by the קמיצה kemitzah and מהקמיצה ואילך mehakemitzah v'eilach
מצות כהונה. mitzvas kehunah. So you're right, in theory the owner could
transgress as well. Okay so let's take a look. תנו רבנן. tanu
rabbanan. לא ישים עליהם שמן. lo yasim aleihem shemen. Do not put
on them. I think it's עליה, aleha, that ו vav looks like
an or עליהם, aleihem, I think it's a misquote. Anyway what? Okay,
לא ישים עליה שמן lo yasim aleha shemen ואם שם פסל v'im
sam pasal and if you put it on you've invalidated. יכול לא
יתן עליה לבונה ואם נתן פסל, yachol lo yiten aleha levonah v'im
nasan pasal, maybe the same is true with the לבונה? levonah? תלמוד
לומר כי חטאת talmud lomar ki chatas because it is a חטאת,
chatas, this is again by the מנחת חוטא. Minchas Chotei. יכול, yachol,
so what does that mean? כי חטאת, ki chatas, it's still a
חטאת chatas even if you did it, it still retains its status.
Now of course it doesn't tell you which is true for the
שמן shemen or the לבונה levonah but we're using our logic based
on the physical reality
to say that by the לבונה levonah it's different
because. What made you say that by the adding the oil it's
invalid but the adding of the לבונה Levonah you can fix it
and it remains valid? ומכשירני בלבונה, U'machshirni be'levonah, פוסלני בשמן שאי אפשר
ללקטו, posolni beshemen she'ee efshar lekato, I invalidate the oil because it's
impossible to remove it, to gather it up, it got absorbed. ומכשירני
בלבונה שאפשר ללקטה, U'machshirni be'levonah she'efshar lilketa, I say the לבונה's Levonah
kosher because it's possible to pick it up and to remove it.
Oh, well you can say, you say it's like on the top
layer, you can just skim it off.
Okay, but say by the oil... Yeah, but then it's no longer
the original... Yeah, but then it's already I presume... first of all
that would be a very special circumstance and second of all, how
would you know it remained on the top layer and anyway, once
it's, you know, it anyway it's already obviously into the מנחה Minchah
itself so the מנחה Minchah has to be transformed so it's clear
that it should... if something has to be פסול posul it's that
which has, you know, which has inserted itself into the מנחה, Minchah,
it's reached... has changed the nature of the מנחה. Minchah. Okay. בעא
רבא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן. Ba'ei Rava bar Bar Chanah
amar Rebbi Yochanan. So רבא בר בר חנה Rava bar Bar Chanah
asked of רבי יוחנן: Rebbi Yochanan: נתן לה לבונה שחוקה מהו? Natan
lah levonah sh'chukah mahu? Okay, what let's say you took this לבונה,
Levonah, which are like these like we said like crystals, and you
ground them, like you took, you know, rock crystals and you made
it into like table salt, like salt crystals made into table salt.
So now it's going to embed itself in the surface of the
מנחה. Minchah. Now remember this מנחה Minchah has no oil, it's basically
just flour. Okay, that's what a מנחת חוטא Minchas Chotei is: flour,
no שמן, shemen, no לבונה. Levonah. Okay, so you go ahead and
you put it in, it's going to embed itself within the flour,
you're not going to be able to sift it through and get
it out. Is that going to... would that also become invalid? Or
do we say because it's really just sitting side by side of
each kernel, it has not really like you know inserted itself into
the kernels themselves, it's mixed with the kernels but it has not
like infused itself into the מנחה, Minchah, maybe that's not enough to
invalidate. So...
What do you do with this flour, you bake it? Is nothing
going to happen to it?
Yeah, the question is do you add water to it. Is it
just flour because we've already said that you'd add...
what? You literally could add water to it.
Right, because the גמרא Gemara talked about that you can't do קמיצה
kmitzah by מנחת חוטא minchas chotei and there was a debate whether
you could add water. Thank you. What do you do with the
flour? You put... you put it on the מזבח Mizbeach and the
כהנים Kohanim eat the rest.
Do they make a candy?
No, but once... once it's offered they can do whatever they want
and as Michael correctly reminds us, the גמרא Gemara before had a
debate about whether you're allowed to add water to it even before
you do the קמיצה kmitzah to make it easier to do the
קמיצה. kmitzah. So... but right, but afterwards you just...
so it's just a pile of flour.
Exactly, maybe with water, maybe it's some dough.
Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara wants to know whether now of
course the interesting question here is, even if it wouldn't invalidate, you
know, because you understand the logic, I mean there's actually something that
we deal with in... in what do you call it? In תערובות
כשרות Ta'aroves Kashrus all the time which is there's two basic definitions
of mixtures of food. One is called לח בלח lach belach where
the things are really like infused and mixed up like in I
don't know some blood falls into your chicken soup, to take an
extreme example, and then there's יבש ביבש, yavesh beyavesh, things are side
by side and you don't know which is which, like you have
one טריף treif piece of meat mixed up with five kosher pieces
of meat. Then there are cases which are somewhere in the middle
like you have let's say you know non-kosher flour, let's say it
was טבל tevel or something, mixed with your kosher flour, but they're
all mixed up. So if you look at each
kernel it's יבש ביבש, yavesh beyavesh, right, there's one thing that's just
next to another, but obviously from a more experiential point of view
it's like לח בלח, lach belach, it's all mixed up together as
one big unit. So anyway to some degree that's what the גמרא
Gemara is saying here, it's saying it's not as bad as oil
in this case, it's not like it's really infused into it, it's
really sitting next to, but it's sitting next to in a way
that you can't really extract it. So to what degree does that
change the definition? Now even if it doesn't change the definition and
invalidate, the funny thing is that how are you supposed to exactly
do a קמיצה? kmitzah? Right, if you did a קמיצה kmitzah it
would be a קמיצה חסירה, kmitzah chaserah, right, because a קמיצה kmitzah
would not be all flour, it would be flour with with you
know לבונה levonah in it. So why... so it should be impossible
to bring it anyway because you can't do the קמיצה. kmitzah. For
some reason the גמרא Gemara is ignoring that question and wants to
know maybe because it's not infused into it, maybe it does not
invalidate. So let's see what the answer is. Okay, so בעי מיניה
רב הונא מרבי יוחנן: Ba'ei minei Rav Huna meRebbi Yochanan: נתן לה
לבונה שחוקה מהו? Natan lah levonah sh'chukah mahu? If it's ground up
what's the הלכה? halachah? משום דאפשר ללקטה והא לא אפשר ללקטה? Mishum
d'efshar lilketa v'ha lo efshar lilketa? Is the reason we said it
was kosher because what the ברייתא brayta said explicitly because it could
be gathered up and this can't be gathered up? It's all you
know this לבונה levonah mixed with flour. או דילמא, O dilma, or
do we say, משום דלא מיבלע? mishum d'lo mivla? Because it's not
absorbed? והא נמי לא מיבלע, V'ha nami lo mivla, this isn't absorbed
so although it said you can pick it up, but you know
that was just describing that reality, but really it would be sufficient
that it's not absorbed, and since it's not absorbed it does not
change its identity. Which is the story? So it says תא שמע
ta shema come and hear: הלבונה יקטנה. Ha'levonah yekatena. Our משנה Mishnah
says if it's... if it's the לבונה levonah you fix it by
picking it off. So you see it's because it can be picked
off. So חדא ועוד קאמר. Chada v'od ka'amar. Maybe it's saying one
and more than that, meaning: חדא דלא מיבלע, Chada d'lo mivla, first
of all it's not even absorbed, ועוד v'od and in this you
know normal case it's even better יקטנה yekatena you can even pick
it up. So תא שמע, Ta Shema, come and hear, דלבונה יקתנה.
Dilvana yoktana. Our משנה Mishnah says if it's the לבונה, Levana, you
fix it by picking it off. So you see it's because it
can be picked off. So דילמא חדא ועוד קאמר. Dilma chada ve'od
ka'amar. Maybe it's saying one and more than that. Meaning חדא דלא
מבלע. Chada delo mivla. First of all, it's not even absorbed. ועוד,
Ve'od, and this, you know, a normal case is even better, יקתנה,
Yoktana, you can even pick it off. Meaning, yes, it's true all
these texts talk about picking off, but that's because they could say
that. Is it necessary to have the ability to pick it off
or maybe it's sufficient that it's not
absorbed? So that's so do so that'll we're going to try again.
תא שמע, Ta Shema, come and hear. מכשירני בלבונה, Machshirni belivona, the
ברייתא, Braita, I will say that the לבונה Levona is כשר kasher
if it's put on this מנחה, Mincha, שאפשר ללקטה, she'efshar leloktah, because
it's possible to pick it off. So again you see it talks
about picking it off. So הכא נמי חדא ועוד קאמר. hacha nami
chada ve'od ka'amar. There also they're saying like more than is necessary.
So but I don't know, I know these ברייתות Braitot talk about
picking off, but I don't know if that is technically what is
required. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי הוי עלה, mai hava ala,
what was the upshot of this? So אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק,
Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, תניא, tanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
Braita. מנחת חוטא ומנחת קנאות, Minchat chotei u'minchat kena'ot,
the מנחה Mincha of a sin and the מנחה Mincha for jealousy
for the סוטה, Sota, שנתן עליה לבונה, shenatan aleha levona, if you
put לבונה levona on it, מלקטת את הלבונה וכשרה, melaktet et halevona
ukesheira, you pick off the לבונה levona and it becomes כשרה. kesheira.
ואם עד שלא ליקט לבונתה, v'im ad shelo liket levonatah,
if before you picked off the לבונה, levona, חישב עליה, chishav aleha,
you had a מחשבה, machshava, which was your מחשבה, machshava, again our
friend פיגול, pigul, חישב עליה בין חוץ לזמנו בין חוץ למקומו, chishav
aleha bein chutz lizmano bein chutz limkomo,
whether it was a פיגול pigul thought to eat at the wrong
time or a normal invalidating non-פיגול pigul thought to eat in the
wrong place, פסול ואין בו כרת, pasul v'ein bo karet, it is
פסול, pasul, there is no כרת. karet. It doesn't become פיגול. pigul.
Why doesn't it become פיגול pigul if it still has the לבונה
levona on it? Because while it still has the לבונה levona on
it, although you can fix it, it still is not at this
moment it's not כשר, kasher, so therefore your thought does not make
it פיגול. pigul. Now the question is so what why is it
saying why is it saying it's פסול?
pasul? So either it's פסול pasul because like תוספות Tosafot says, forget
your thought, it's פסול pasul because it's got the לבונה levona on
it. Okay, that's why it's פסול, pasul, got the לבונה levona on
it. רש"י Rashi said it's פסול pasul because although since you had
a wrong thought, even though you can't it doesn't qualify as פיגול
pigul because there's another invalidity going on, it's enough of a wrong
thought to make it invalid. Okay the נפקא מינה nafka mina would
be what happens now after this thought, now you remove the לבונה.
levona. According to תוספות, Tosafot, the only problem was it had the
לבונה, levona, so now you remove the לבונה levona you're okay. According
to רש"י, Rashi, your thought was enough to invalidate it and even
after you remove the לבונה levona it remains invalid.
Did we see the same thing by all the other times when
you know
those something had another פסול?
psul? This is the only time we have a reversible פסול. psul.
So there's nothing really to compare it to. The real question is
going to be whoever heard of a reversible פסול? psul? So we'll
get to that now.
But well the other question is, I mean, and this is what
I was struggling with, because why isn't it just a regular לא
תעשה lo ta'aseh and you know you're right.
So the I mean the משנה, Mishnah, I mean the ברייתא Braita
here learns it out right?
היא, Hi, this is היא, hi, פסול, pasul, that this isn't really
I don't see I
think in the end you're right, in the end it's getting it
from the word היא, hi, היא, hi, only this way is it
the כשר. kasher. Okay look, that's not such a problem because as
I said even by the לבונה levona you don't really even understand
the הוה אמינא hava amina by not מבלע mivla because how can
you do a קמיצה? kmitza? It'll be קמיצה חסירה. kmitza chasera.
Okay and that's partly why what I was saying, you know, even
with שמן, shemen, so you know I mean it just seems it's
an איסור issur so then just take off what you put on.
If it was only a technical problem of a קמיצה חסירה, kmitza
chasera, right then you could suggest those things, but presumably it's learning
it from the word היא. hi. Okay, so that's what it says,
that if you're you had your פיגול pigul thought now it's not
yet it doesn't yet become פיגול pigul because it has the לבונה
levona on it. ואם משליקט לבונתה, v'im misheliket levonatah, if after you
remove the לבונה, levona, חישב עליה חוץ למקומו, chishav aleha chutz limkomo,
then it goes back to being כשר, kasher, חישב עליה חוץ למקומו
פסול chishav aleha chutz limkomo pasul and there is no כרת. karet.
So if your thought was a wrong place, that invalidates without כרת.
karet. חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, wrong time, that's a פיגול pigul thought,
פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת. pigul vechayavin alav karet. It is it becomes
כרת. karet. Now how does this prove our point? Very simple. Because
you were trying to argue, the respondent is, that you don't actually
have to remove the לבונה. levona. As long as the לבונה levona
is not absorbed, it's sufficient for the קרבן korban to be כשר,
kasher, right? That's the argument. So here it's very clear because according
to you, I mean תוספות Tosafot really already asked this. How could
you think you don't have to remove the לבונה? levona? The משנה
Mishnah says remove the לבונה, levona, the ברייתא Braita says remove the
לבונה. levona. So maybe we would have thought that that's just a
מצוה, mitzvah, but בדיעבד bedi'avad what he's suggesting is it's כשר kasher
even without removing the לבונה levona since it doesn't get absorbed. Right?
Because he gives a case where it's impossible to remove the לבונה,
levona, it's ground up, and he wants to suggest it's still כשר.
kasher. So according to him the idea is that yes you're supposed
to remove the לבונה levona but even if you can't maybe it
remains כשר. kasher. So here it's clear not that way. Here it's
clear that your פיגול pigul thought has no meaning until the לבונה
levona is removed. So you see that as long as the לבונה
levona remains mixed up, it is considered פסול. pasul. So once we
see that as long as the לבונה levona is mixed up it's
פסול, pasul, obviously if it's impossible to remove it's going to remain
פסול. pasul. Okay so this is how we've answered the question. All
these things talk about removing the לבונה. levona. Until the לבונה levona
is removed it's פסול. pasul. Once the לבונה levona is removed it's
כשר. kasher. It's not about being absorbed, even if it's not absorbed,
it has to be removed. If it can't be removed, it remains
פסול. pasul. Fine. Yes.
Is it only לבונה? levona? What if you throw a mint in
there or anything?
So that's a very good question. So you don't transgress is a
negative prohibition, לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה. lo yasim
aleha shemen v'lo yiten aleha levona. The question that you do have
to ask, and that sort of goes back to what I was
saying before, was that how do you, why don't you have a
קומץ חסר? kometz chaser? Right? Why don't you say your קמיצה kmitza
is lacking, it's not full of all the right ingredients, it's got
a little of the other ingredients? And to some I don't know
the full answer because to some degree, in the past we suggested
adding other ingredients like we said you could add water to this,
water's never said in the תורה. Torah. And maybe that we learn
out from other מנחות minchos that, where also we assume water even
though it's not written. But remember the גמרא Gemara for example had
suggested fruit juices, and the only problem it had with that was
whether fruit juice could be מחמיץ machmitz or not מחמיץ. machmitz. So
it's not so clear to me. I mean logically, my intuition would
be that anything not explicitly mentioned is a foreign ingredient and if
it doesn't invalidate directly, at least indirectly it means that you don't
have a, your קומץ kometz is חסר. chaser. But I don't know
the answer. The test would be a מנחת כוהנים. minchas kohanim. מנחת
כוהנים Minchas kohanim you don't have a קמיצה. kmitza. So the question
would be, let's say you added other ingredients to a מנחת כוהנים,
minchas kohanim, right? That I don't know. That I would actually say
might be כשר. kasher. What my
intuitively, although I could look into it, I would say that if
you add an extraneous ingredient, it certainly makes it a קומץ חסרה
kometz chasera because you don't have the full, your קומץ kometz is
lacking the full amount of the right ingredients. But a מנחת כוהנים
minchas kohanim if it's not שמן shemen and לבונה, levona, who knows,
maybe it is כשר, kasher, I'd have to look into it. Okay,
so now we have that. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to turn
its attention to the question of this very bizarre phenomenon that it
becomes פסול pasul and you can make it re-כשר kasher again. Okay,
and again the way we're saying it based exactly on the exchange
that Reuven and I just had, it's not just that technically you
could take the קמיצה. kmitza. We're calling it פסול. pasul. How does
it become פסול pasul and כשר kasher again? Don't we have a
principle known as what? Michael? Something that's become פסול? pasul?
Oh, you're saying מי שנראה ונדחה? mi she'nirah v'nidche? דיחוי? Dichuy? דיחוי.
Dichuy. It's נדחה.
nidche.
For a while it was פסול. pasul. How does it become כשר
kasher again?
So, if I'm a כוהן kohen is married to a wife that
I'm not allowed and allowed to be a כוהן kohen anymore once
I divorce her?
But דיחוי dichuy is not about people. דיחוי Dichuy is about objects
and it might even not be about live objects, בעלי חיים, ba'alei
chayim, but certainly is about inanimate objects. Okay, so how can it
be פסול pasul as a קרבן korban and then כשר kasher again?
That's the גמרא's Gemara question. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Now, this is a very
interesting גרסא girsa of the גמרא. Gemara. I'll read it the way
we have it and then I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot says.
Here's the way we have it. ותיהוי פך. V'tehave pach. Why isn't
when the לבונה levona is on it like a פך, pach, like
a, like a vessel, which רש"י Rashi says like of oil, meaning
why when the לבונה levona is on it didn't it, isn't it
like oil spilled on it, which totally invalidates it?
ומאי פסלה במחשבה? U'mai pasla b'machshava? Why did the מחשבה machshava even
for the invalidate, the פיגול pigul thought מחשבה machshava invalidate? Even though
it didn't make it פיגול, pigul, at least invalidated it. How did
it have the power to invalidate? If it was פסול, pasul, the
thought should have done nothing. Okay, דיחוי הוא, dichuy hu, it was
נדחה nidche and it should not do anything. That's a very complicated
question. ותיהוי פך V'tehave pach etc. Why not just say it's דיחוי?
dichuy? How does this thing stop being כשר kasher and become כשר
kasher again? So תוספות Tosafot actually says this is an amazing sort
of, if you're an academic תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says the original
גרסא girsa of the גמרא Gemara was ותיהוי דיחוי. v'tehave dichuy. That
was it. Let it be דיחוי, dichuy, let it be pushed away,
how does it become כשר kasher again? Then somebody came in and
glossed to explain it in the words ותיהוי דיחוי v'tehave dichuy in
the margin, wrote what was the question, ומאי פסלה במחשבה, umai pasla
b'machshava, why did the מחשבה machshava invalidate? Which תוספות Tosafot says what's
the question? Forget the מחשבה. machshava. The question is how does it
become invalid and then become valid again? And then he wrote, he
wrote פירוש. peirush. Here's an explanation to the גמרא, Gemara, ומאי פסלה
במחשבה, umai pasla b'machshava, and some later person thought the word פירוש,
peirush, פ'י peh yud with a slash, was the word פך. pach.
So תוספות Tosafot has a whole explanation of how this גרסא girsa
got this way. תוספות Tosafot says the גרסא girsa is ותיהוי דיחוי.
v'tehave dichuy. Let it just be דיחוי. dichuy. But somebody stuck in
the words, why is מחשבה machshava a problem? פירוש, peirush, and פירוש
peirush became פך pach and the whole thing. So you can take
a look at this תוספות ותיהוי דיחוי Tosafot v'tehave dichuy if you
want to see a real academic תוספות, Tosafot, okay, where he recreates
how the text got this way. Anyway, so let's just deal with
תוספות's Tosafot version. Let it be דיחוי. dichuy. How does something stop
being good and become good again? ותיהוי דיחוי. V'tehave dichuy. So who?
So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says חטאת קריה רחמנא.
chatas karya rachmana. Because the פסוק pasuk that told us that it
remains good even with the לבונה, levona, חטאת היא chatas hi is
telling us that because it can be fixed, it's going to retain
its status of a חטאת. chatas. You're right, it is bizarre. It
is in this middle stage where now it's פסול pasul and becomes
כשר kasher later, but because the תורה Torah is insisting that it's
called a חטאת, chatas, it's telling us that it does not get,
it's not נדחה, nidche, it's not totally pushed off. Now that is
implicitly for the reason you can fix it, which is what we're
about to see. Where was I? רבא אמר הא מני חנינא המצרי
היא. V'Rava amar ha'mani Hanina Hamitzri hi. This is חנינא המצרי Hanina
Hamitzri who דלית ליה דיחוין. d'leis leh dichuyin. He never holds that
דיחוי dichuy is a problem. דתניא D'tanya חנינא המצרי אומר, Hanina Hamitzri
omer, חנינא המצרי Hanina Hamitzri says by יום כיפור Yom Kippur that
let's say the שעיר המשתלח sa'ir hamishtaleach died, what do you do
and you already have the blood of the other שעיר sa'ir that
you're in the middle of doing the sprinkling. and forth. So what
do you do?
So he says אפילו דם בכוס, afilu dam b'kos, even if the
blood is in the vessel, מייתי חבירו שלא בהגרלה, meisi chaveiro shelo
b'hagralah, you bring another goat if the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtale'ach died,
without doing the lot. How do you do lot if one of
them is in blood? Okay, so you don't do the lot, you
just bring another goat and say that's now the new שעיר המשתלח,
se'ir hamishtale'ach, ומזווג לו, u'mizaveig lo,
and you partner it with the blood. So there the blood for
a while was נדחה, nidcheh, until you had the other goat picked
out, this blood was pushed away, and nevertheless you can reuse it
now that you've fixed the problem. So you see there are those
that say דחויה dichuya is not a problem and we would be
going according to that opinion. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, רב
אשי Rav Ashi says no, even without חנן המצרי Chanan Hamitzri and
even without a special פסוק, pasuk, there's a reason this is not
דחויה. dichuya. Why not? כל שבידו לא הוי דחויה. kol she'b'yado lo
havei dichuya. Anything you can fix is not דחויה. dichuya. If it's
totally in your control, it never really gets pushed aside. Okay, the
idea of דחויה dichuya is not just that it's invalid, but if
it's invalid it almost gets like rejected. Something that could be, oh
wait, I can just fix it, oh no problem, I'll just fix
it, okay, that never really got rejected, it was always, you know,
seen as something that has just a little thing that can be
fixed. Now of course the question is what constitutes בידו? b'yado? Is
going running and getting another goat בידו? b'yado? I mean, you know,
which are, how much בידו b'yado is בידו? b'yado? But this is
very easy. You spilled some לבונה levonah on it? No problem. Just
scoop the לבונה levonah off, right, it's not דחויה. dichuya. It's sort
of like, you know, it's sort of like the two-second rule by
the, everybody knows exactly what I'm talking about, right? You drop the
nipple of a bottle on the floor, you pick it up, you
blow on it. Two seconds didn't really happen.
Five seconds! Okay, I'm being more מחמיר. machmir.
Anyway, five seconds, five.
Definitely five seconds.
All right, five-second rule.
Anyway, so it's a big deal, it's over double.
Okay, so that's what he says. That's not דחויה. dichuya. That's why
it remains כשר. kasher. Now of course while it's still there it's
a problem, but there's an idea of seeing the problem from the
very beginning as being just temporary and fixable and therefore not enough
to push the thing sort of off the center stage. Okay.
Okay. אמר רב אדא, Amar Rav Ada, so רב אדא Rav Ada
says כוותיה דרב אשי מסתברא, k'vasi d'Rav Ashi mistabra, it makes sense
like רב אשי Rav Ashi that this is the because it's בידו
b'yado that it's never considered דחויה. dichuya. דמאן שמעת ליה דאית ליה
דחוין, de'man shamis lei d'is lei d'chuyin, who normally is concerned with
דחויה? dichuya? רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דמאן,
de'man, and because we found in the משנה Mishnah by again this
case of the goats on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, ועוד אמר רבי
יהודה, v'od amar Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said נשפך הדם
ימות המשתלח. nishpach hadam yamut hamishtale'ach.
If the blood is spilled you have to let the שעיר se'ir
which is sent away die because you now can't get another pair
for it because this was pushed off. מת המשתלח ישפך הדם, meis
hamishtale'ach yishapeich hadam,
if the משתלח mishtale'ach died you have to spill the blood, again
because it for a while could not be used. So you see
that he holds of a דחויה dichuya problem. ואילו היכא דבידו, ve'ilu
heicha d'b'yado, but we know that when it's in his, it's in
your control to fix it, תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
Baraisa, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, כוס היה ממלא מדם התערובות,
kos hayah memalei midam hatarovos,
on פסח Pesach after they brought all the קרבן פסחs Korban Pesach
at the end of the day, they would fill up a vessel
from the blood that's mixed on the floor of the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. וזרקו זריקה אחת כנגד היסוד, v'zarko zrikah achas k'neged hayesod,
and they would do one last throwing on the on the base
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, why? Because maybe somebody's blood from somebody's קרבן
פסח Korban Pesach accidentally spilled, never got thrown on the מזבח, mizbe'ach,
it's mixed up with all the other bloods, so you pick it
all up and you throw it again and therefore you're okay. So
you see he holds that even though there was a while it
wasn't used, if you can fix it, it's not דחויה, dichuya, even
though in principle he holds of דחויה. dichuya. Now there's two interesting
points here. Number one is the case by the goats was also
בידו, b'yado, right? I mean, go get new goats, go get another
goat. Why is it not בידו? b'yado? Why is that considered דחויה?
dichuya? So unless you say that the problem there was was that
because you need to start with a matched pair when you get
one, it's not but then it's not a דחויה dichuya problem, then
the problem is because it wasn't a matched pair to begin with.
So the fact that so it shows you that not every בידו
b'yado is equivalent. Some things are very quick fixes and some things
are more complicated fixes and not every בידו b'yado is equivalent. The
other interesting thing is it's not clear to me why the blood
on the floor of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is considered to
be דחויה. dichuya. That blood was never unusable. If that blood was
caught in a כלי שרת, klei shareis, which is what we have
to be talking about, and then it spilled. So it's not like
it's how is that any less usable? Because it's not right now
in a כלי שרת, klei shareis, I guess would be the problem.
So I'm just thinking what makes it not usable? Pick it up
and throw it. You know, it's not exactly the famous לבונה levonah
which is פסול pasul while the לבונה levonah is there. Maybe the
point is that while it's on the floor it's not in a
כלי שרת klei shareis and you have to get it on the
מזבח mizbe'ach with a כלי שרת, klei shareis, not straight from the
floor. That's probably the idea. ולא נתקדש ברצפה? v'lo niskadesh b'ritspah? What?
Yeah, but there's anyway there's no way you can bring it to
the מזבח mizbe'ach in its form, you have to get it in
a different you know form, maybe that's the point.
Maybe there was dirt on the floor, something else that would mix
up.
No, but then we've never solved that problem. Presumably the only problem
other than it has yet to be brought is that it's not
in a כלי שרת. klei shareis. Okay, so anyway that's how you
see that בידו b'yado fixes things. Okay. Now we go on and
that's why this מנחה minchah can become כשר kasher again and it's
not דחויה. dichuya. Okay. אמר רב יצ, Amar Rav Yitz, now we
get back to the... how you transgress and we talk about the
שיעור. Shiur. So let's take a look. אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan. So
רב יצחק בר יוסף Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef says in the name
of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan: נתן משהו שמן, Natan mashehu shemen, how
much do you have to put on how much in order to
transgress?
So even if it's the smallest amount of oil על גבי כזית
מנחה al gabei kezayit mincha as long as the amount of the
מנחה Mincha is a כזית kezayit worth פסל pasal you've invalidated. Okay
well let's take a look. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the reason?
לא ישים Lo yasim it says do not place and שימה sima
is כל שהוא kol shehu even the smallest amount. To place there's
no sense of a minimum amount to place something, it could mean
even the put a drop of something on, so there's no amount
of oil. Now how do you know that the מנחה Mincha has
to be a כזית? kezayit? עליה Aleha on it, עד דאיכא שיעורא
ad d'ika shiura
it has to be some size of significance. Now Michael says maybe
a קמיצה kemitsa but remember this is not just about doing the
קמיצה kemitsa and being מקריב makriv it, it's to be on the
part of the מנחה Mincha that you're not doing the קמיצה kemitsa
on. So therefore מנחה Mincha also has significance as something that's eaten
right that's what the כהנים kohanim are going to do to the
rest of it. So therefore we assume the smaller of the שיעורים
shiurim which is a כזית. kezayit. Okay, Michael's idea of קמיצה kemitsa
would have been possible but it's not limited to the קומץ komets
and we assume a כזית. kezayit. That's how much you need for
the prohibition of oil. ואמר רב יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן
V'amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan now how about how
about the prohibition of לבונה? levona? Wait let's just see the לבונה.
levona. נתן כזית לבונה על גבי משהו מנחה פסל. Natan kezayit levona
al gabei mashehu mincha pasal. We reverse it when it comes to
the לבונה. levona. It has to be a כזית kezayit worth of
לבונה levona not a משהו mashehu on how much of a מנחה
Mincha even the smallest amount. Why why are we reversing it? מאי
טעמא? Mai ta'ama? לא יתן כתיב Lo yiten ktiv do not place.
So placing as opposed to שים sim I don't know it does
not have good different English words. שים sim is maybe I don't
know putting, יתן yiten was like giving, don't give on it. So
that's more the idea to give on to something, although normally talks
about giving to a person but to give onto something עד דאיכא
נתינה ad d'ika netina you have to give something of significance. I
gave you something suggests it was a thing there was something of
substance. So it has to be something of substance it has to
be a כזית. kezayit. Now how do you get on even a
כל שהוא? kol shehu? עליה Aleha on it. So or how does
that tell you even the smallest amount of a מנחה? Mincha? Before
we said it means something of significance so top of ס עמוד
א samech amud aleph הוי ריבוי אחר ריבוי havei ribui achar ribui
it's you know it's an increase after an increase. It already said
עליה aleha by the oil, don't pour on it oil. And on
it means something of significance. Now it's saying don't give on it
לבונה levona and on it again means something of significance. It's making
a double demand. So we have our general principle אין ריבוי אחר
ריבוי אלא למעט ein ribui achar ribui ela lema'et that a double
is that we're insisting on it yet again we actually mean it
doesn't have to be so big and therefore even if you put
it on a small amount of a מנחה. Mincha. Okay so when
it comes to the oil a little bit on a כזית kezayit
when it comes to the לבונה levona it has to be a
כזית kezayit worth because of נתינה nitna to give but even on
a small amount of a מנחה. Mincha. We'll read to the י"ד
yud dalet and then we'll hear your question Michael. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי
V'ika d'amri some say אמר רב יצחק בר יוסף בעי רבי יוחנן.
amar Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef baei Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
actually asked a question about about this. Once we've now established that
the לבונה levona is a כזית kezayit because יתן yiten to give
means something of significance a כזית kezayit he wants to go back
and say maybe that should inform the prohibition of the oil. So
he says נתן משהו שמן על גבי כזית מנחה מה natan mashehu
shemen al gabei kezayit mincha mah what is the story if you
only do a little bit of oil on even a כזית kezayit
of a מנחה? Mincha? מי בנין שימה כנתינה Mi banyan sima k'netina
do we translate the word שימה sima to place through the lens
of נתינה netina to give? And the same way נתינה netina to
give means a כזית, kezayit, שימה sima also means a כזית kezayit
so you'd have to do a כזית kezayit worth of שמן. shemen.
או לא O lo or do we say no שימה sima means
any amount even a כל שהוא? kol shehu? תיקו Teku so we
don't know. So it's clear that נתינה netina means a כזית. kezayit.
The question is שימה sima normally can mean a small amount but
in the context of נתינה netina maybe it means a כזית. kezayit.
One comment one more comment and then we'll hear what Michael has
wants to ask. The idea that נתינה netina is a כזית kezayit
so תוספות Tosafot has a very interesting question of do we always
say that or not. He discusses other cases first of all רש"י
Rashi says where do we know נתינה netina is a כזית kezayit
anyway giving is a כזית? kezayit? Actually from this last week's פרשה.
parsha. This last week's פרשה parsha it said that if somebody eats
קודש בשגגה kodesh bishgaga eats you know sanctified things in error which
חז"ל chazal say means a תרומה teruma that he should not because
it belongs to the כהן. kohen. ונתן לכהן את הקודש V'natan l'kohen
et hakodesh he gives the כהן kohen the קודש kodesh and therefore
the כהן kohen and חז"ל chazal understand what that means is if
I accidentally ate a כהן's kohen תרומה teruma I have to give
him food in exchange and that food then becomes automatically תרומה teruma
that's my compensation becomes תרומה. teruma. And since the problem there was
was that I ate it and I'm giving him something therefore that
can be eaten we understand that נתינה netina not only has to
be food in that context but it had to be a כזית.
kezayit. So that's where we learn out נתינה netina is a כזית.
kezayit. תוספות Tosafot deals with other cases where the concern might more
be about monetary issues and נתינה netina might be a פרוטה pruta
not a כזית. kezayit. Right it's always a question what lens are
you looking at something through. Right you know what do they say
what is it like a cynic knows the what is it?
The price of everything and the value of nothing.
Right. So if you're always looking at something through the lens of
how much does it cost right maybe נתינה netina is it's got
to be worth a dollar. Right not everything is about what it
costs. Sometimes the thing is like how about functions, what it's worth
and so on. So here it's interesting that we're talking about foods
and we're talking about נתינה בכזית. netinah bekezayit.
תוספות Tosfos discusses sometimes where נתינה netinah might be בפרוטה beprutah depending
on our lens. The other interesting question that תוספות Tosfos raises which
goes back to a point we said about a week ago that
I just wanted to repeat is תוספות Tosfos says but one minute,
we don't say it by תרומה, Terumah, by תרומה Terumah it says
that you should be give it to the כהן. Kohen. If you
look at the first wide line here on סמך עמוד א, Samech
Amud Aleph, תוספות Tosfos says like this, or not the first wide
line, five lines before the wide line, the line starts with the
word בתרומה. bi-Trumah. He says, וקצת קשה בתרומה דכתיב תתן לו, vkas
kasheh bitrumah d'ksiv titein lo, give the כהן Kohen the תרומה. Terumah.
אמאי כאיסא דאזיל פטרה את הכרי? amai ke-isa d'azil patrah es hakeri?
Why do we say even one little grain exempts a whole big,
you know, what a heap of a mound of grain. אטו בעי
כזית כנתינה דשמעתין, atu ba'ei kezayit kenetinah dishmaitin, let's require a כזית,
kezayit,
how are you giving the כהן Kohen anything of substance? And as
I told you, he doesn't have an answer. And anyway as I
told you about a week ago there are those that explain that
there actually are two מצוות mitzvos of תרומה. Terumah. One is to
exempt the grain, to make the grain no longer טבל, tevel, and
there even the tiniest amount. But there's a separate מצווה mitzvah to
give something to the כהן. Kohen. And to give something to the
כהן Kohen it actually does have to be something of substance and
it cannot be a tiny amount. And to see that there's two
aspects to the מצווה mitzvah of תרומה. Terumah. So here it's interesting
that תוספות Tosfos raises that question. He doesn't give that answer, he
sees it all as one and he doesn't leave his question answered.
Michael, you had a question.
Yeah, I was going to say it was that when we were
saying on a כזית, kezayit, you know, it seems that it's still
too small because what are you going to do with the כזית,
kezayit, like you can't even do a קמיצה kemitza out of that.
A כזית kezayit is
because a קמיצה kemitza is two כזיתים, kzeitin, so I think you
wouldn't even have done anything.
But who says it's a קמיצה? kemitza? מנחה Mincha can also be
eaten, the remnants of the מנחה. Mincha.
Right, but you can't eat the remnants until you do the קמיצה,
kemitza, and the קמיצה kemitza has to be two, you
know, has to be a קמיצה שיעור. kemitza shiur. Right. So what
if, you know, if since you're not, I guess you're throwing out
the, I guess you're throwing out, you're doing
something wrong to the מנחה. Mincha. You're saying that since the only
transgression is before the קמיצה kemitza anyway, by the שיריים shirayim we
learn you don't transgress, why don't I measure by the קמיצה? kemitza?
Okay, but at least you've done something of substance that you've ruined
a part of the edible part of the מנחה. Mincha.
But you know, so I understand, anyway normally we'll just assume the
minimum, you know.
But if we're worrying about a קמיצה חסר, kemitza chaser, it should
be even the littlest amount on the littlest amount, because
you know, you can put שמן shemen on, the whole idea that
you did it only on a כזית kezayit of it means you
separated a part out and you're only doing it or you limited
it to a part of the vessel. So that part might be
the part that I do the קמיצה kemitza on, that part might
be the אכילה. achila.
No, I put a little bit on a teeny bit and then
it gets all mixed up and then you know I
don't know when I do my קמיצה. kemitza. I'm sure that's the
case. Why do I have to look at it as though it's
function relating to the קמיצה kemitza of the מנחה, Mincha, why not
look at it as related to the edible part of the מנחה?
Mincha? That seems to be the assumption.
You can't have one without the other, that's what I'm saying.
Yes you can, if the whole point here is you didn't put
it on the whole שיעור, shiur, you put it on a separate,
you separate out a piece or you put it at one edge
of the vessel, so maybe that's the part I'm going to eat.
Okay, whereas then you don't have, then you don't have the whole
problem. The whole problem is you only put it on a small
part of the מנחה, Mincha, you have to define a small part.
Right, and you come back you don't know where it is, so
I don't know why you're assuming that, that's not the case. Okay,
תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. נתן שמן על שייריה. Natana shemen al shiray'ha.
Okay, so now the end of the משנה Mishna says if you
put oil on the remnants it's כשר. kasher. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן. Lo yasim aleha shemen v'lo yitein.
Do not put oil on it and don't put on it לבונה.
levonah. יכול בשני כהנים. Yachol bishnei kohanim. Maybe it's all requiring two
כהנים. kohanim. Now what's the הוה אמינא hava amina it would require
two כהנים? kohanim? So I'll read you the way תוספות Tosfos says
it. תוספות Tosfos gives than רש"י. Rashi. תוספות Tosfos says the question
here is if I do the same thing on one מנחה. Mincha.
First I put שמן. shemen. Remember what happened if I put שמן,
shemen, what did it make the מנחה? Mincha? פסול. passul. Now I
put לבונה levonah on. Have I transgressed? Maybe the same way I
don't transgress if I make a פסול מנחה חמץ, passul mincha chametz,
right, because it's already, because it's already פסול, passul, maybe I don't
transgress if I put לבונה levonah on a מנחה Mincha that I
already put שמן shemen on. Or maybe not. The Torah links them,
maybe the same way you can do מחמץ אחר חמץ, mechameitz achar
chametz, if you continue to make it as חמץ chametz even though
it's already חמץ chametz you transgress, maybe לבונה levonah after שמן shemen
I would transgress. Maybe it was פסול passul for some other reason,
it was פיגול, pigul, it was יוצא, yotzei, I wouldn't, but if
it's שמן shemen and לבונה levonah maybe I transgress. So that's the
question. Do I need, תוספות Tosfos says when it says שני כהנים
shnei kohanim it doesn't mean two כהנים, kohanim, it means two מנחות.
Minchas. Like שני כהנים shnei kohanim we envision that each כהן kohen
with his מנחה Mincha would deal with a מנחה. Mincha. So יכול
בשני כהנים, yachol bishnei kohanim, maybe I only transgress these things if
we're dealing with two separate כהנים kohanim which means two separate מנחות.
Minchas. תלמוד לומר עליה. Talmud lomar aleha. בגופה של מנחה הכתוב מדבר.
Begufa shel mincha hakatuv medaber. On it, on the מנחה Mincha itself,
meaning even on the same מנחה Mincha you put the שמן shemen
don't put the לבונה levonah and yes you will transgress if you
put the לבונה levonah on the מנחה Mincha with the שמן shemen
even if it's the same מנחה. Mincha. So that's one read of
תוספות. Tosfos. The other read he has at the answer means the
exact opposite. That no, עליה aleha only on one individual מנחה Mincha
but you will transgress, you know, that
each prohibition is for a separate מנחה, Mincha, but if it's the
same מנחה Mincha you don't transgress when you do one after the
other. But for תוספות Tosfos that's the issue here. Do you transgress
if you do לבונה levonah after שמן shemen when it's already פסול
passul and I would say if you read the גמרא Gemara that
way the simple answer is is that yes you do transgress. Even
if it's only one מנחה Mincha you will transgress both. Okay.
וגופא כמנחה כתיב הדבר ולא בכהן v'gupha k'mincha kesiv hadavar v'lo b'kohein
ולא בכהן v'lo b'kohein not with a different כהן kohein which here
תוספות Tosafos takes to mean not with a different מנחה. mincha. יכול
לא יתן כלי על גבי כלי Yachol lo yitein kli al gabi
kli maybe it you can't even put oil in a vessel on
top of your מנחה mincha ואם נתן פסל v'im nasan pasal and
maybe if you did you invalidate, תלמוד לומר עליה Talmud lomar aleha
on it directly. בגופה של מנחה כתב דבור B'gupha shel mincha kesiv
dibur don't put the oil on the מנחה mincha as opposed to
don't put the oil in a vessel and the vessel on the
מנחה. mincha. So not only do you not invalidate, you also do
not transgress. But according to תוספות Tosafos the interesting question here although
he has two variations of what the answer is, is whether you
transgress if it already became פסול pasul because of your שמן, shemen,
you could continue to transgress because of the לבונה. levonah. Okay, let's
take a look now at the next משנה. mishna. So that was
two משניות mishnayos that wrapped up which things get oil, which things
get לבונה levonah and so on, the basic ingredients. Now we talk
less about the ingredients and more about the procedures and what do
you do with a מנחה? mincha? So the תורה Torah says that
you take the מנחה והגישה אל המזבח mincha v'higishah el hamizbeiach that
you bring it to the altar. We're going to say you take
the מנחה mincha and you touch it to a corner of the
מזבח. mizbeiach. Does this apply by all מנחות menachos or not? So
let's take a look.
And some מנחות menachos also get waved. So that's now going to
be the focus here, הגשה hagashah and תנופה. tenuphah. יש טעונות הגשה
ואין טעונות תנופה Yeish teunos hagashah v'ein teunos tenuphah there are some
that are touched to the מזבח mizbeiach but do not get waved.
הגשה ותנופה Hagashah u'tenuphah some get touched and waved. תנופה ולא הגשה
Tenuphah v'lo hagashah things that get waved and not touched that will
include even non-מנחות menachos but okay. לא תנופה ולא הגשה Lo tenuphah
v'lo hagashah neither get waved nor get touched to the altar. ואלו
טעונות הגשה ואין טעונות תנופה. V'eilu teunos hagashah v'ein teunos tenuphah. Now
here are the ones that get הגשה hagashah and not תנופה. tenuphah.
Interesting, remember when it came to oil and לבונה levonah we first
mentioned the ones that had both. Here we're mentioning the one that
only has הגשה. hagashah. You know why? Because we want to start
with the big list. So when it came to oil and לבונה
levonah the standard was oil and לבונה levonah and you had 10
things. Here when it came to waving and הגשה hagashah the standard
is just הגשה. hagashah. Waving is an exception. Define waving. We're going
to define in the גמרא Gemara but it's up and down and
back and forth. Okay but we'll get to it in the גמרא.
Gemara. With hands? Yes. In the כלי? kli?
In the כלי, kli, yeah, not the מנחה mincha is in the
כלי kli and the כלי kli is in the hands. Correct. Okay
we'll discuss it in the גמרא. Gemara. But okay so here the
standard is הגשה hagashah and therefore without תנופה tenuphah and therefore that's
the one we list first and again there are going to be
10. So let's count. Okay. ואלו טעונות הגשה ואין טעונות תנופה. V'eilu
teunos hagashah v'ein teunos tenuphah. מנחת הסולת minchas hasoles the simple one
of flour and just plain flour and oil. והמחבת v'hamachavas והמרחשת v'hamarcheshes
the
you know the frying pan, the deep frying pan. והחלות v'hachalos והרקיקין
v'harkikin
and the חלות chalos and רקיקין rekikin are two variations of מאפה
תנור ma'afei tanur things that are baked in an oven. The תורה
Torah says חלות מצות בלולות בשמן ורקיקי מצות משוחים בשמן chalos matzos
belulos bashemen u'rekikei matzos meshuchim bashemen
one which is more bread-like, the other which is more wafer-like. So
we have סולת, soles, מחבת, machavas, מרחשת, marcheshes, חלה chalah and רקיק
v'rekik that's five.
Just the same list as the others.
The same list as the others. Five based on the first four
מנחות menachos mentioned in the תורה Torah in ויקרא. Vayikra. But we
understand that the חלות chalos and רקיקין rekikin are variations of מאפה
תנור ma'afei tanur so that's five. מנחת כהנים minchas kohanim even if
it's brought by the כהנים kohanim אין הנאכלת ein hane'acheles none get
eaten. מנחת כהן משיח minchas kohein mashiach or the כהן גדול kohein
gadol half in the morning half in the evening, also it's obligatory
and nothing gets eaten. Nevertheless that is הגשה hagashah without תנופה. tenuphah.
Same הלכה. halacha. All of these are private מנחות menachos until now.
The five variations of a normal individual, כהנים, kohanim, כהן משיח, kohein
mashiach, מנחת נכרים minchas nochrim non-Jews. So I thought it said עובדי
כוכבים ovdei kochavim and that was more of an... yeah עובדי כוכבים
ovdei kochavim is never the original גרסא. girsa.
I have
no idea why it was changed. Okay non-Jews. מנחת נשים minchas nashim
women also fascinating why it gets included. There is no different halachic
status to a מנחה mincha of women. There is to a קרבן
korban that you don't do סמיכה semichah not to a מנחה. mincha.
But for some reason it's mentioning it, as I mentioned yesterday I
think it's just to get to the number of 10 because now
we're up to nine. And מנחת חוטא minchas chotei a מנחה mincha
of a sinner all of those get הגשה. hagashah. Now here is
where the list becomes a little different than yesterday because Michael yesterday
what was it different? You didn't have מנחת חוטא minchas chotei what
did you have yesterday?
We had מנחת עומר. minchas omer.
מנחת עומר. minchas omer. We had עומר. omer. Why? Because there's a
different rule that dictates. The rule that dictates about
what gets הגשה hagashah what gets touched to the מזבח mizbeiach is
a מנחה mincha of which is actually burnt on the מזבח. mizbeiach.
So a normal מנחה mincha everything is burnt, a קומץ. komets. Even
מנחת כהנים minchas kohanim the entire thing is burnt. So that some
gets burnt. So if something is getting burnt on the מזבח mizbeiach
it gets הגשה. hagashah. Okay so therefore you have the last case
of מנחת חוטא minchas chotei some of it got burnt. Right, it
gets burnt and you do a קמיצה kemitsah therefore it's going on
the מזבח. mizbeiach. Why does עומר omer not in here? Well first
of all the answer is because עומר omer gets waved. So עומר
omer yes a part does get burnt, it does get הגשה hagashah
but it's in the special category of having both. Okay that's why
it's not in this list. So this list but it does include
מנחת חוטא minchas chotei because here it's not the question of oil
and לבונה levonah which is specifically not about the sinner's מנחה, mincha,
it's about the rule of הגשה. hagashah. And הגשה hagashah is anytime
a part of the מנחה mincha gets burnt it gets הגשה. hagashah.
The only reason עומר omer is not here is because עומר omer
also gets waved. So let's keep on going, those are the ten
things that get only הגשה. hagashah. Now we go on. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omeir, מנחת כהנים ומנחת כהן משיח אין בהם הגשה.
minchas kohanim u'minchas kohein mashiach ein bahem hagashah. He says, so the
מנחה mincha of כהנים kohanim does not get הגשה. hagashah. Oh, something
gets burnt. For him, that's not enough. לפי שאין בהם קמיצה. lefi
she'ein bahem kmitzoh. It's not enough for him that some part of
it gets burnt. It has to be only when... when a קמיצה
kmitzoh gets burnt. When not all of it gets burnt. When some
gets burnt and some gets eaten. וכל שאין בהם קמיצה אין בהם
הגשה. v'chol she'ein bahem kmitzoh ein bahem hagashah. If there's no קמיצה,
kmitzoh, there's no הגשה. hagashah. It's true the מנחת כהנים minchas kohanim
all gets burnt. That doesn't work for me. It has to be
the קמיצה's kmitzoh burnt and the rest is eaten. So he has
a different standard. So when it comes to קמיצה, kmitzoh, before we
get... when it comes to הגשה, hagashah, before we get to תנופה,
tnufa, that's based on the principle that a part of it gets
burnt, so it would exclude for example,
like, what would be a good thing that's not burnt? שתי הלחם.
shtei halechem. Nothing gets burnt, right? Or the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim.
What goes with the לחם הפנים? lechem hapanim? Only the לבונה levonah
gets put on the מזבח. mizbeiach. The שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, only
the lambs go on the מזבח. mizbeiach. Nothing gets burnt, there's no
הגשה. hagashah. And there's a question, what if it all gets burnt?
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says no הגשה, hagashah, the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma says yes. Okay, something else, right, now there is something not
on this list that does get burnt, that is מנחת נסכים. minchas
nesachim. That's right, the one that comes with the animals that all
gets burnt. That's not on the list because that doesn't come on
its own accord. So the basic implicit principle here is, it gets
burnt and it comes on its own. Comes on its own excludes
מנחת נסכים, minchas nesachim, gets burnt excludes things like שתי הלחם, shtei
halechem, I'm sorry, like or לחם הפנים, lechem hapanim, which don't get
burnt, only the לבונה levonah gets burnt. And then the whole debate
is about the מנחת כהנים, minchas kohanim, what happens if it all
gets burnt? Does that also get הגשה? hagashah?
Let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, I guess. Lots of
הגשות hagashos in one משנה. mishnah. I guess now there's more to
discuss.
There's more to discuss, right, because then we're going to have to
do the תנופה tnufa discussion and yes, there's more to discuss. So
again, I don't know in the original break up of the משנה,
mishnah, I haven't checked, but at least the editor of the גמרא
Gemara decided to break this up for more focused discussion. Okay, so
we are now only looking at the first part of the list.
אמר רב פפא. Amar Rav Papa. So רב פפא Rav Papa said,
we had this exact statement of רב פפא Rav Papa yesterday. כל
היכא דתנן עשר תנן. kol heicha d'tnan eser tnan. Whenever we have
this big list of מנחות, minchos, yesterday it was about oil and
לבונה, levonah, here it's about הגשה, hagashah, it's always ten מנחות minchos
that are listed. מה קמשמע לן? ma kamashmalan? What are you telling
me? Of course, I can count to ten. So לאפוקי מרבי שמעון,
l'apokei m'Rabbi Shimon, to exclude from רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, דאמר מחצה
חלות ומחצה רקיקין יביא, d'amar mechtza chalos u'mechtza rekikin yavi, that when
you bring the מנחה mincha of מאפה תנור, ma'afeh tanur, it doesn't
have to be... rather than saying either ten loaves of one or
ten loaves of the other, he actually says you're allowed to bring
five loaves of each. Five loaves of the חלות, chalos, five loaves
of the רקיקין, rekikin, or ten of one, ten of the other.
I'm sorry, just gave the option ten of one, ten of the
other. So according to him, there's a third variation. It's not just
חלות chalos or רקיקין, rekikin, it's also חלות chalos and רקיקין. rekikin.
So according to him, we'd have eleven on the list, not ten.
קא משמע לן דלא. ka mashmalan d'lo. Our משנה mishnah is exactly
saying ten, nice round number, implicitly rejecting רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that
you could bring a מאפה תנור ma'afeh tanur of a combination of
five and five. Okay, fine, that was parenthetical. Let's get now to
the core of the משנה mishnah about הגשה. hagashah. מנא הני מילי?
minan hanei milei?
Where do you know this? About which things get הגשה? hagashah? דתנו
רבנן. d'tano rabbanan. Because the rabbis said: אילו נאמר. ilu ne'emar. Had
it said... so the פסוק pasuk says והבאת את המנחה אשר יעשה
מאלה לה'. v'heiveisa es hamincha asher yei'aseh mei'eileh laHashem. This is at
the end of where it brings about bringing the מנחה. mincha. Let
me just find the פסוק.
pasuk. והקריבה אל הכהן והגישה אל המזבח. v'hikrivah el hakohein v'higishah el
hamizbeiach.
Oh, it's not in this room. He might be downstairs. I don't
know.
So his office looks
like it's started and completed. Right, so the תורה Torah says at
the beginning of ויקרא, Vayikra, ונפש כי תקריב קרבן מנחה לה', v'nefesh
ki takriv korban mincha laHashem,
and gives you all the variations of the מנחה. mincha. And after
it gives you all the variations, it tells you how you bring
the מנחה. mincha. It says והבאת את המנחה אשר יעשה מאלה לה',
v'heiveisa es hamincha asher yei'aseh mei'eileh laHashem, from any of these, והקריבה
אל הכהן, v'hikrivah el hakohein, bring it to the כהן, kohein, והגישה
אל המזבח, v'higishah el hamizbeiach, the כהן kohein brings it to the
מזבח, mizbeiach, touches it to the מזבח. mizbeiach. So here it's quite
explicit as opposed to yesterday where we were discussing לבונה, levonah, and
לבונה levonah is only mentioned in סלת, soles, in the first one.
The חז"ל Chazal assumed that it applies to all. Here the תורה
Torah is very clear. Whatever type of מנחה mincha you bring, הגישה
אל המזבח, higishah el hamizbeiach, bring it to the מזבח. mizbeiach. Okay,
so let's take a look. אילו נאמר והבאת אשר יעשה
מאלה, ilu ne'emar v'heiveisa asher yei'aseh mei'eileh, you should bring, it didn't
say you should bring the מנחה, mincha, but you should bring that
which you will make לה' laHashem to God, והקריבה אל הכהן והגישה,
v'hikrivah el hakohein v'higishah, bring it to the כהן, kohein, he'll touch
it to the מזבח, mizbeiach, הייתי אומר אין לי שטעון הגשה אלא
קומץ בלבד. hayisi omeir ein li shetaun hagashah ela kometz bilvad. I
might think it only applies to the קומץ, kometz, because only the
קומץ kometz is אשר יעשה מאלה לה', asher yei'aseh mei'eileh laHashem, is
only the one going straight to God. מנחה מניין? mincha minayin? How
do I know it applies to... the הגשה, hagashah, the touching to
the מזבח, mizbeiach, applies to the entire מנחה? mincha? תלמוד לומר מנחה.
talmud lomar mincha.
It says you shall bring the מנחה mincha והגישה אל המזבח. v'higishah
el hamizbeiach. Okay, that's just פשט pshat of the תורה. Torah. מנחת
חוטא מניין? minchas chotei minayin?
Now I only know that about the four or five standard מנחות
minchos that are mentioned at the beginning. How do I know about
the מנחה mincha of חטא, cheit, which is no oil and no
לבונה? levonah? How do I know that also does הגשה? hagashah? תלמוד
לומר את המנחה. talmud lomar es hamincha.
The extra את es comes to include even ones
not... נאמר כאן ne'emar kan מנחת חובה minchat chova ונאמר כאן v'ne'emar
kan מנחת נדבה. minchat nedava. So we have by the individual in
the first פרשה parsha of ויקרא Vayikra a
obligatory מנחה mincha which is the מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei and we
have a free will מנחה mincha which is mentioned first which is
all the variations of the
מנחה. mincha. מה מנחת נדבה טעונה הגשה Mah minchat nedava te'una hagasha
אף מנחת חוטא טעונה הגשה. af minchat chotei te'una hagasha. I could
have made a logical comparison. The same way an individual free will
מנחה mincha gets הגשה, hagasha, I would have assumed by analogy the
same is true by the later מנחה mincha in ויקרא Vayikra of
the obligatory one. הגמרא Hagemara says one minute, maybe not. מה למנחת
נדבה שכן טעונה שמן ולבונה. Mah l'minchat nedava sheken te'una shemen u'levonah.
Obviously
they're not the same. The free will מנחה mincha you have oil
and לבונה, levonah, so who's to, so of course it's different from
a מנחת חוטא, Minchat Chotei, so maybe only the נדבה nedava gets
הגשה hagasha and not the
חובה. chova. So מנחת סוטה תוכיח. Minchat Sota tochi'ach. No, I'll prove
it from a מנחת סוטה Minchat Sota because מנחת סוטה Minchat Sota
doesn't get oil, doesn't get לבונה, levonah, and the תורה Torah explicitly
says by the מנחת סוטה Minchat Sota as we're going to quote
later that you touch it to the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Yeah, but it
also needs תנופה tnufa too. Okay, so we'll get to that. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says so you see that even without oil
and לבונה levonah you do הגשה. hagasha. No, מה למנחת סוטה שכן
טעונה תנופה. Mah l'minchat sota sheken te'una tnufa. You see that Michael
could have written it. The מנחת סוטה Minchat Sota requires תנופה, tnufa,
so you can't prove that that gets הגשה hagasha anything gets הגשה
hagasha because that's special. So the גמרא Gemara says well okay מנחת
נדבה תוכיח. Minchat nedava tochi'ach. But I'll prove that תנופה tnufa doesn't
matter from a free will מנחה mincha which doesn't have תנופה. tnufa.
So this is one of those cases in which there are different
characteristics. The underlying commonality is that they all get
הגשה. hagasha. וחזר הדין. V'chazar hadin. And it goes back and forth.
לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה. Lo re'i
zeh k're'i zeh v'lo re'i zeh k're'i zeh. Each one's distinctive characteristics
is not like the other. מנחת סוטה Minchat sota is distinctive that
it gets
תנופה. tnufa. מנחת נדבה, Minchat nedava, a normal free will מנחה, mincha,
is distinctive that it gets oil and לבונה. levonah. But in the
end those are not true about the other case, so you eliminate
the distinctive characteristics. הצד השוה שבהן, Hatzad hashaveh shebahen, in the end
the common denominator is ששוו לקמיצה. sheshavu l'kmitza. Both of them you
do קמיצה kmitza on whether it's a סוטה sota or a
מנחת נדבה. minchat nedava. ושוו להגשה. V'shavu l'hagasha. They get הגשה. hagasha.
אף אני אביא מנחת חוטא. Af ani avi minchat chotei. So I'll
include also מנחת minchat of a
sinner ששוו להם לקמיצה וששוו להם להגשה. sheshavu lahem l'kmitza v'sheshavu lahem
l'hagasha. Since you do קמיצה kmitza on it you should also do
הגשה hagasha on it. So I could have learned it out from
logic. No, here would be the question.
מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן הוכשרו לבא בעשיר כבעני. Mah l'hatzad hashaveh
shebahen sheken huchsharu lavo b'ashir k've'ani. Those types of things whether it's
a סוטה sota or whether it's a free will, even a rich
person can bring. A מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei is only brought by
a poor person. The whole idea of a מנחת חוטא Minchat Chotei
is a certain type of a חטאת, chatat, again very rare type
of a חטאת, chatat, עולה ויורד, oleh v'yored, which varies based on
the person's wealth. So only a poor person can bring a מנחת
חוטא. Minchat Chotei. It's not similar. It has something that makes it
stand out from the rest. And therefore maybe it doesn't get הגשה.
hagasha. תאמר במנחת חוטא שלא הוכשרה לבא בעשיר כבעני? Tomar b'minchat chotei
shelo huchshra lavo b'ashir k've'ani?
So maybe because it can not be brought by anybody, it can
only brought by a poor person, maybe it's different and it doesn't
get הגשה. hagasha. That'd be a very negative religious message wouldn't it?
Since only a poor person's מנחה, mincha, we're not going to do
הגשה hagasha to the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Anyway, thankfully we don't say that.
תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so that's why the verse has to teach
את המנחה. et hamincha. The extra את et comes to include. So
Michael, your question, how do I know what את et is including,
obviously you see here the גמרא Gemara essentially, or the ברייתא braita
has shown its hand. We have a logic which is compelling us
to want to include חוטא, chotei, but because you can technically make
a difference, we need that extra word in the פסוק. pasuk. But
obviously how we learn that word is informed by the logic that
we're coming to the פסוק pasuk with. Okay, let's just do a
little bit more. רבי שמעון אומר. Rabbi Shimon omer. Now רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says, he focuses on a different part of the פסוק.
pasuk. He's really not disagreeing yet. In the end we're going to
disagree about כהנים, kohanim, but he's not disagreeing yet. So רבי שמעון
אומר Rabbi Shimon omer והבאת, v'heiveita, it says
and you shall bring לרבות מנחת העומר להגשה. l'rabot minchat ha'omer l'hagasha.
So you use the את et to include a מנחת חוטא. Minchat
Chotei. We have another מנחה mincha we have to include, the מנחת
העומר. Minchat Ha'omer.
Yeah, but doesn't that need, doesn't that need תנופה tnufa too?
So he's only, yeah, but we're not talking about תנופה, tnufa, we
just want to know הגשה. hagasha. Okay, so I'm going to use
and you shall bring to include even the מנחת העומר Minchat Ha'omer
gets הגשה. hagasha. וכן הוא אומר, V'chen hu omer, and how do
I know והבאת v'heiveita refers to the מנחת העומר? Minchat Ha'omer? Because
it has the word והבאתם, v'haveitem, והבאתם את עומר ראשית קצירכם אל
הכהן. v'haveitem et omer reishit ktzirchem el hakohen. Okay, so therefore that's
how he throws in מנחת העומר. Minchat Ha'omer. Again, nobody's disagreeing להלכה,
l'halacha, they're learning different things out. והקריבה, V'hikrivah, you shall bring it.
It's again for the פסוק pasuk והקריבה אל הכהן. v'hikrivah el hakohen.
So that's the other thing we have to include, לרבות מנחת סוטה
להגשה, l'rabot minchat sota l'hagasha, the מנחת סוטה. Minchat Sota. Now how
do I get that out of the word והקריבה? v'hikrivah? וכן הוא
אומר V'chen hu omer והקריב אותה אל המזבח. v'hikriv otah el hamizbei'ach.
You should bring it to the מזבח. mizbei'ach. Of course everybody asks
if it's right there in the פסוק pasuk והקריב אותה אל המזבח,
v'hikriv otah el hamizbei'ach, why did you need to make a link
to this to say הגשה? hagasha? It's right there that it gets
הגשה. hagasha. So maybe to tell you where you do the הגשה,
hagasha, which is more explicit in our פסוק. pasuk. than it is
by the סוטה. Sotah. But that's how we know the סוטה Sotah
gets הגשה. hagashah. Okay? ודין הוא, ve-din hu, and I could have
maybe learned it out logically: ומה מנחת חוטא שאינה טעונה תנופה טעונה
הגשה, u-mah minchat chotei she-einah te-unah tenufah te-unah hagashah, מנחת סוטה שטעונה
תנופה אינו דין שטעונה הגשה? minchat sotah she-te-unah tenufah eino din she-te-unah
hagashah? If a sinner's מנחה minchah you do הגשה hagashah which we
already learned out, certainly a סוטה Sotah you should do הגשה hagashah
because you also even do תנופה tenufah by a סוטה. Sotah. No,
מה למנחת חוטא שכן באה חטים. mah le-minchat chotei she-ken ba'ah chitim.
Maybe מנחת חוטא minchat chotei is more important, it comes from wheat
flour as opposed to מנחת סוטה minchat sotah that comes from barley
flour, so maybe it's not important to do
הגשה. hagashah. מנחת עומר תוכיח. minchat omer tokhiach. How about the עומר
omer we just included? That comes from barley. מה למנחת עומר שכן
טעונה שמן ולבונה. mah le-minchat omer she-ken te-unah shemen u-levonah. No, that's
more important because that gets oil and לבונה. levonah. The מנחת סוטה
minchat sotah doesn't get oil and לבונה. levonah. מנחת סוטה minchat sotah
is like the worst of all worlds. It's only barley, it's not
even wheat, no oil, no לבונה. levonah. So maybe if it's so,
you know, so second grade, third grade, maybe it doesn't get הגשה.
hagashah.
And a woman, why not?
There you go. You can save all that for when we learn
סוטה Sotah but מנחת חוטא תוכיח. minchat chotei tokhiach. So okay, I'll
prove it from מנחת חוטא, minchat chotei, that doesn't have oil and
לבונה. levonah. וחזר הדין, ve-chazar ha-din, לא ראי זה כראי זה ולא
ראי זה כראי זה. lo re'i zeh ke-re'i zeh ve-lo re'i zeh
ke-re'i zeh. Each one's distinctive characteristic is not like the other.
הצד השוה שבהן ha-tzad ha-shaveh she-ba-hen ששוו לקמיצה she-shavu le-kmitzah ושוו להגשה,
ve-shavu le-hagashah, אף אני אביא מנחת סוטה af ani avi minchat sotah
ששוותה להן לקמיצה she-shavtah la-hen le-kmitzah ששוה להן להגשה. she-shaveh la-hen le-hagashah.
I'll include therefore the one of the סוטה Sotah because there's קמיצה,
kmitzah, there's also going to be הגשה, hagashah, so I don't need
a פסוק. pasuk. No, מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן הוכשרו לבוא סולת.
mah le-ha-tzad ha-shaveh she-ba-hen she-ken hukhsharu la-vo solet. תאמר מנחת סוטה שהוכשרה
לבוא קמח. tomar minchat sotah she-hukhsharah la-vo kemach.
All of the other ones at least come סולת, solet, סולת solet
is fine flour. Again, a distinctive characteristic of the מנחה minchah of
a סוטה Sotah is קמח kemach which is more like bran flour,
not fine flour. So again, it has one characteristic which everything else
is not like, and therefore maybe you don't do הגשה hagashah by
מנחת סוטה. minchat sotah. As Bobby said, you know, because
it's about this woman and sin and so on, it's really the
worst of all מנחות, minchot, so maybe it doesn't get, you know,
הגשה. hagashah. תלמוד לומר והקריבה. talmud lomar ve-hikrivah. Therefore it says והקריבה
ve-hikrivah to tell you that even that you do it. So we'll
continue with this tomorrow, but at this stage what we learned is
that basically any מנחה minchah that you do קמיצה kmitzah for, which
you do, you do הגשה. hagashah. We learned it's in the תורה,
Torah, it's by centrally by the main מנחות, minchot, but from those
we've included sinner, עומר, omer, סוטה, Sotah, all these things you do
קמיצה kmitzah for. The debate of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the
חכמים Chachamim is what if you burn it and don't do קמיצה
kmitzah for, what about מנחת כהנים? minchat kohanim? So that has not
yet been explicitly but you can see the ברייתא braita is following
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon because the way the ברייתא braita articulates the
common denominator is not that some of it is burned but that
if it has קמיצה. kmitzah. If it has קמיצה, kmitzah, it has
הגשה, hagashah, and that's following רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's approach that says
you don't do הגשה hagashah for מנחת כהנים. minchat kohanim. Okay, so
to be continued tomorrow.